Preliminary Inventory of the Joseph John Hertmanowicz Papers, 1916-1941
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph John Hertmanowicz Papers,
1916-1941
XX357
Hertmanowicz, Joseph John
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings and speeches, memoranda, and resolutions, relating to the history, economy, and foreign policy of Lithuania and to the movement for Lithuanian independence. Includes appeals from Lithuanian-American organizations to the U.S. government urging recognition of the independence of Lithuania.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Lithuanians--United States.; Nationalism--Lithuania.; Lithuania.; Lithuania--Economic conditions.; Lithuania--Foreign relations.; Lithuania--History.; United States--Foreign relations.
Container List
- An Appeal for Starving Lithuania, by Kleofas Jurgelionis, Chairman of the Chicago Lithuanian Day Committee, Lithuanian National Relief Fund. Copy of pamphlet, date between August 31, 1916 and November 1, 1916 (Box 1)
- Precis of Lithuanian History to 1882, by Joseph J. Hertmanowicaz, 1917?
- The Cause of Washington, by Joseph J. Hertmanowicz. Address delivered in Chicago, 1918 February 22
- Resolution adopted by the Lithuanians of Chicago at the Celebration of the 142nd Anniversary of the Declaration of Independence, 1918 July 4
- United States of Lithuania, Memorandum to the Press by J. J. Hertmanowicz, Vice President, Lithuanian Council of Chicago, 1918 December 28
- The Romance of Eastern Europe, by Joseph J. Hertmanowicz, 1919 September?
- Lithuanian Appeal to the United States Congress, 1919 June 9
- Memorial to the Foreign Relations Committee, United States Senate, Washington, D.C., 1919 August 29
- A Spirit Arms Could Not Crush, by J. J. Hertmanowicz. Copied from the Dearborn Independent, 19th year, No. 32, 1919 June 7
- Draft petitions to the United States Congress (2 forms), 1919
- Memorandum from the Lithuanian Executive Committee to the Department of State, 1920 January 17 [very important]
- Memorandum for the American Red Cross on the Sanitary and Food Situation in Lithuania, 1920 January 24
- Commentaries on the Hertmanowicz Documents, by M. W. Graham, 1935 October
- The Resurrection of Lithuania, by Joseph J. Hertmanowicz. Subtitle: The Second Anniversary of Lithuanian Independence (February 16, 1918 -February 16, 1920). Part one of an elaborate historical memorandum citing verbatim references to Lithuania in her medieval greatness from a wide variety of historical sources and secondary materials
- Resolutions adopted at the Lithuanian Mass Meeting Held at Auditorium, August 15, 1920. A Lithuanian mass reply to the Colby Note
- Address at Protest Meeting, Seventh Regiment Armory, Chicago, 1920 October 30
- Lithuanian Protest against Polish Aggression, 1920 October 31
- Open Letter to Prince Lubomirski, 1920 November 15. Used to accompany the preceding item
- Memorandum to President Harding, 1921 May 31
- Memorandum to the Secretary of State, 1921 June 24
- The Lithuanians, by Joseph J. Hertmanowicz. Address delivered 1921 November 16
- Memorandum on the Klaipeda Uprising, 1923 January. Released to the press by the Lithuanian Kleipeda Committee. Page 4 contains a passage in the original which was deleted in the official version given to the press
- Memorandum from E. J. Harrison, 1926 June 15, regarding official translations of certain Lithuanian documents
- The Foreign Trade Relations of Lithuania, by Matas J. Vinikas, 1923
- Lithuanian Foreign Policy, by M. Lozaraitis, Lithuanian Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1935 May 31. Translation